Hey guys, welcome back. In this session,
we are going to talk about how you can
do test data management and TDS which is
test data services uh in Tricentis TSA.
Okay. But before we move into uh how TSA
helps you uh with the whole test data
management, let's first understand what
is test data management and why it is so
important um in test automation.
Now if you have worked with uh any test
automation tool or any test automation
framework, test data plays a major
part. And in some of the test automation
frameworks, the whole framework is
driven by test data. And these type of
frameworks are also popularly known as
datadriven frameworks.
Now in most of the uh automation tools
or frameworks uh we generally use uh
external data sources to manage our test
data and this management is mostly uh
manual right. So uh we can create test
data from different tools or different
techniques but in order to manage the
test data either we have to write some
code on our own or we have to do it
manually. Okay. And this external data
sources could be anything. It could be
Excel, it could be a database, uh it
could be XML, right? Or JSON. So there
are multiple data sources which can be
used to uh store that test data. And
then to create test data, you can use
different uh something like you can use
random test data generators or different
tools to generate this test data. Right?
So the storing and creating of test data
uh is still not a problem. uh that can
still be done but management uh is a
time consuming and also quite
challenging process right so identifying
the correct test data for your execution
or your test cases is very important
okay and test data management is this
process of identifying and managing the
right test data for uh any system you
are going to test okay you have to Make
sure that for each test execution you
have got unique test data because if you
are using a particular test data in one
test execution cycle and then um again
in the second test cycle if you use the
same test data there are high chances
that your test will fail because the
application may not accept the same test
data. Right? So for example, if you are
going to create a account or a
registration form you're filling and uh
you are using the same email address,
right? The application may not uh accept
the the same email address for the
registration because that registration
has been completed by that user using
that particular email address. Right? So
this is one example where you can see
that you cannot repeat that test data
next time. So it's very important that
you use uh unique test data and you
manipulate the test data in a way that
every test execution run has a unique
set of test data. Okay. Also there are
lots of scenarios uh when you work with
different uh applications right. So
whenever you are testing any particular
application it is not just a web
application right. So there is a backend
application then there there could be
some other front-end applications which
are communicating with this web
application right. So generally a
process u comprises of multiple
applications and we need to test that
particular process. Okay. So when we are
using test data, we have to make sure
that all these applications can process
this test data and uh the data can flow
from one application to another
seamlessly uh without any problems.
Okay. Also as I said uh manually
maintaining uh all this test data and
managing it is not very efficient. It's
a very uh slow process and it's also
time-taking. Right? So all of these
points you see uh highlight the
importance of test data management
right. So if a tool can help you with
this test data management process then
your job becomes much easier. You can
use unique test data you can uh use test
data across different um applications
and you can also track and update your
test data accordingly.
Okay. And this is where uh TSka comes
into the picture right. So TSA has this
way of managing test data which is
called the test data management and for
this uh it uses the TDS which is called
the test data services. Okay. Now it
overcomes all the challenges um which we
discussed earlier and it provides a
central place where you can register
your test data after you created it and
then you can use the right test data uh
in all your test cases. You can track
and update state of every test data
throughout your whole life cycle and you
can also manage your data uh so that it
can be shared across different
applications. Okay. So test data
services has different uh standard
modules which are available part of your
standard.tsu
uh where you will find all of these
different steps or you can perform all
of these different steps. Okay. So as
you can see in this picture uh this is
the test data management and then u
these are the different processes right
which could be different applications
uh which are basically processing this
test
data. So uh the first process uh it will
create some test data and that it will
be stored or registered uh in the TDM
and then uh this test data will be used
by a process second process right uh
which will modify the test data and then
again it will be stored in TDM and then
it will be again used across the process
three and that continues right um and
the test data management it takes care
of all the other things like uh you are
using the right test data, you are
tracking and you can update your test
data and you can also uh share it with
different processes. Okay, so all of
this could be done uh by test data
services which is TDS and it's a TSCA
server component. You can set it up on
the TSA server. Okay. And uh the back
end would be a database or you can also
store it uh in your local memory. But
this is where uh you can create
different repositories and uh you can
create different uh data uh in this
particular
repository. So let's uh go to our TSCA
server and let's look at how um this
test data services work and how we can
use different uh modules to work with
our test data.
So now um when I open my TSA server
landing page which is localhost 80080
this is where we had set up our TSCA
server. So the test data services is
part of the TSA server installation. So
once you are installing TSCA server TDS
uh will also be installed automatically.
Okay. So you don't need to do anything
uh additional to install uh or set up
TDS or test data management uh in TSCA
server. It will be part of your Tska
server installation. Now to access it uh
you have to go here under test data
management in your server landing page.
Now the test data management or TDS uh
it has got a web interface like you can
see here. Okay. And here you can create
repositories, you can create test data
types, you can also create uh your test
data, you can delete, you can manage uh
you can do all all kinds of stuff right
uh on the web interface. But all of this
could also be done on using the standard
modules in TSCA commander. So we'll try
to have a look both ways. First we will
try to see how you can do it in the web
interface like right here and then we'll
see how you can go to Tuska commander
and you can automate this whole process
so that it can be integrated with your
whole testing process.
Okay. So test data management or TDS has
got its own repositories like uh we had
repositories for a workspace in Tuska
commander. We have repositories for test
data management. Okay. And as you can
see these are the three repositories
which I have created. I can go ahead and
uh edit them. I can go ahead and also
delete them. Right? So there is a delete
and the edit button here. So I can go
ahead and delete this repository right
from here also and also you can delete
the database which is uh which is linked
with this particular repository. Okay.
So that will uh delete that particular
repository. Uh as I said I can also edit
the name and description for this
particular repository. Okay. Uh the data
repository. So let me remove this and
then I will explain. So this data
repository this is uh the default
repository for TDS and it is already
present. Uh once you open this page you
will see this data repository. Obviously
it will not contain anything inside this
but uh we can always go ahead and add
our type. Okay. So uh the most important
part of your test data services or test
data management is a type and a
repository. Right. So the first step is
to create a repository and then inside
that you will have different types.
Okay. Now these types um or the test
data types could be anything. Okay. Uh
it can be divided based on your
functionality of the application or
different parts of your application,
different processes of your application
or it could be just different teams or
different applications in itself. Okay.
So it completely depends on you how you
want to define your types but you need
to have a particular type before you can
create any test data. Okay. So we'll
we'll look at an example. U so after we
create a type then you can create uh
different test data inside this type.
Okay. Now if I can go back here uh first
let me show you how you can create a
repository like this default repository
or the other repositories which were
present already uh in my TDS right so
you have to click on this create
repository and then it will ask you for
some details which you can fill and then
you can save so that will basically
create your own repository
okay so to start off uh we need to give
it a name first right so I can call it
uh test first or test repository.
Obviously, the name cannot contain uh
any spaces or any special characters.
So, do take care of it. Okay. And then
uh you can also enable authorization if
you want but that can be done on the
tricus service configuration side. Uh we
are not going to look at it. Uh there
are different types of repository which
you can create. The default one is
SQLite. But this will be basically
stored um in a local folder. You can see
uh the location of this C program data
triccent is TSCA server test data
service uh and then it will create a DB
file. Okay. So this is basically if you
don't have a database for your test data
then you can create it uh in this
particular folder or this using this SQL
DB. uh but if you have something like
MSSQL or Oracle, you can use them. You
can provide all the details for your uh
database server like the server URL, the
database, the username, password, the
schema and then click on test
connection, right? And then uh you can
just go ahead and save it. You can also
just use the connection string if you
want. Uh just pass the connection string
here and uh the schema if it is
required. Okay. Similarly for Oracle it
is the same. You need to provide a
connection string then test connection
and then you can save it. Okay. But
we'll be using uh for this session we'll
be using the SQLite. Okay. So it will be
stored in this particular location and I
can click on test connection so that uh
it will connect it uh and you will see
this connected sign. Right? So if you
get this that means u there is no
problem with your connection. But if you
don't get this then uh there is a
problem.
Okay. After this uh you can provide a
description for this repository. Okay.
And uh I can do that uh just this is uh
test uh
repository.
Okay. Now sometimes you will see that uh
this save button is not enabled. This
might be because either uh the previous
database file uh is already present uh
in your um in your local in your local
folder or uh maybe you just need to
refresh the TDS service. Okay, but let's
go ahead and try this
again. Okay, so this time you can see uh
after I refreshed the page uh it again
got enabled. So I can test the
connection and then I can again put the
description here. So this is a test uh
repository.
Okay. And then click on save. So that's
going to uh create our test repository.
You can see here this is the test
repository. I can delete and edit as I
said earlier and click on it. And then
you can add a type here.
Now this type as I said uh it can vary
depending on what type of application
you are testing what functionalities you
are testing right so you can u basically
divide your types of test data so that
it can be recognized uh while you are
trying to use this test data right so
for example if I need different test
users right with some uh information of
these users like uh their names their
last name first name email or some other
details, right? So, it could be like a
users file which contains a list of
different users. So, I can create a type
called users. Okay. Um, I can always go
ahead and import this data to to type or
I can create it from uh the modules from
in our TUSCa commander. Right? So,
either way I can do it. uh if I have a
file I can browse it and I can just uh
import that file so that all the data
will be imported uh into this particular
type. Okay. If I have copied it from
somewhere then also I can paste it here
and I can import it. Uh and then you can
also use some sample files which are
provided uh by TSA. So uh for names it
is already there names international
500.json JSON and uh then traffic is
airlines.json JSON right so this will
create some uh sample data right so we
can see that uh so just select the
category and select the type and then
just click on add okay and this will
basically import uh some sample test
data uh into your type users so as you
can see uh I have imported this uh data
for this particular type from a sample
JSON file you can do it uh with
different file formats Um I haven't
checked but it should be uh available
for Excel for uh maybe txt, CSV or JSON
right so you can see here it just looks
like a database table right with
different rows and columns and then you
have got these different records right
so there are around 500 records on this
particular type and it has got this name
uh surname gender region right so you
can also So add your own item here. Once
you click on add item, you will see that
uh it pops up this uh uh a row where you
can enter uh your details, right? So so
for example um I can create this test
data here. Um a new row I can add into
this test data, right? So I can uh add
all the details
here
[Music]
and okay um I can create a new row like
this and uh then just uh click anywhere
and then that row would be added into
your table. Right?
So um this is how you can also delete
and um you can see here uh this lock
sign. You can also lock this particular
row so that it cannot be used by any
other process trying to use this test
data while it is in use. Okay. So we can
lock and unlock the item right from here
or we can also delete this particular uh
record from this particular type. Okay.
So, uh you can consider a type as a
particular table inside your database
and then that table contains different u
records inside this. So, I am trying to
explain it uh in a more database- like
convention, right? It works pretty
similar.
Okay. So, I can also export this data.
You can see all these uh into different
output files like CSV, Excel and JSON.
And then I can import it back into a
different type. Okay, I can put the
encoding, I can put line break and a
separator and I can export it. Okay, so
this will basically export it uh into a
CSV file as you can see here. Um and
then I can easily import the same data.
Okay. So if I add another users uh one
type. Okay. And here I can just import
that particular data as uh we talked
earlier. Okay. So I can select that file
and um I can import it back. Okay. So as
you can see you can easily import and
export data right from this uh user
interface. You can add items, you can
add types, uh you can manage everything
uh for your uh repository uh inside the
test data services. Okay. So all of this
functionality is available on the web
interface when you go into your TSA
server landing page and you go into test
data management. Okay. But all of this
can also be done through TSA commander
and that is the ideal way of doing it.
Right? So you don't want users to go to
your server landing page and uh create
test data there. Uh you it should be
created on the fly uh when you are
running your test automation. So before
you run your um actual test cases your
test data should be already created
right. So let's see how we can use the
standard modules uh to create u types or
to enter data into a particular type.
How you can manage them? how you can
track them and update them right so all
of this can be done using the standard
modules and uh let's see how we can do
that so for this uh demonstration I'm
going to still use our application which
we have been using throughout this uh
whole course so that is the vehicle
insurance uh application right so we
have already developed the automation
test cases for this now let's see how we
can create the test data for this and
maybe we can integrate it uh back to our
test cases so that the test data is
automatically created and we can use the
test data uh instead of uh us generating
the test data within the test cases like
we have done earlier. Okay. So uh for
this uh let me create another repository
here. I'm going to call it sample
app. Okay. And uh I'm going to create
this sample app and inside this I'm
going to now create a type and I'm going
to call it vehicle.
Okay. Uh so we can actually create
different types here. Uh I can create it
for
automo. So let's do
that. Okay. And uh click on add to
create this type. Uh currently there are
no items but that's fine. I don't want
to add items from here. I want to add
items from our test cases. Okay. So,
let's go back to our Tuska commander and
let's go back to our project. Let me
open the project here so that we can
create a new uh folder where we can
create all this test data. Okay. So,
this is our project.
So first let's look at um how we can use
the different modules and what different
modules are present um inside your uh
TDS standard modules and how we can use
them to uh basically manage our test
data and then we will see how we can uh
generate the test data and also use it
uh in our application. Okay. So for that
purpose let me create a new component
folder here. I'm going to call it test
data. Okay. And inside this uh I'm just
going to create another test cases
folder. And inside that I'm going to
create a test case. So generate uh test
data.
Okay. And then inside this we are going
to add different modules. So once you go
into uh your add test step and here you
need to start searching for test data.
Okay.
And once you search for test data, you
will see all the different modules,
standard modules which are available.
Right? So these are all the uh test data
modules. Uh we have got update type,
update item, delete item, import items,
export items. Uh we have got export
module. uh which contains all the
different modules like move item to type
uh find and provide item create and
provide new item right so we'll be using
uh some of them right so we'll be
starting off
by creating and providing a new item
okay so this can be
done so here uh what it will do it will
create a new item inside uh our type
which we have created right? Which is uh
called vehicle. Okay. So uh in this you
have to pass three parameters uh
basically existing or new TDS type.
Okay. Uh you can pass a alias name or
item. Uh if you want to uh basically
provide the alias name otherwise uh it's
not mandatory and then we need to uh
filter our data based on some data
structure. Okay. But first uh let's
provide the type here. So our TDS type
is vehicle as you remember and here uh
here we need to provide a TDS attribute
and a value.
Okay. So um what item uh we want to
create inside this particular uh type
vehicle. Okay. So uh what I want to
create is basically go into the
application and once we go into the
automo page these are the different
items uh which are basically our test
data for this particular application
right because for every test case I'm
going to use this test data like I want
to test with different makes uh
different performance different date of
manufacturers right so I should have
that test data in order to uh test my
test cases with different sets of test
data. Okay. So let's create some test
data for this uh test data type uh in
our test data services. So I want to
first have a item called make, right? So
let's create that and we are going to
call it
make and then um I'm going to give it a
value called BMW.
Okay. And then um I can create another
uh item and then I can give it a value.
So our next item is engine performance,
right? So let's call it engine and I
give it a value something. Okay. And
then uh maybe date of
manufacturer or let's call it DOM.
And uh it should be in this format. So I
will call it 01 01 and
2014. Okay. And then um let's create
number of
seeds. So
[Music]
seeds and that would be
four. And then a fuel type.
So okay. And then I can name it
petrol. After this list
price, right? Uh and here I can give it
uh something like
1500 and uh annual mileage. Okay. So
mileage and let me give it
1,000. So this will basically create the
test data for all the different items uh
present on this particular page. Uh we
can also generate random data. Okay,
instead of giving these uh these values
here, right? Or uh we can also import
this data if we have stored it somewhere
on our Excel file, right? So we can use
the import module but right now I'm just
trying to show you uh what are the
modules which are present and this is
the first module which is to create and
provide new item. So it will basically
create a new item and it will also
provide that item for uh the remaining
part of your test case. Okay. So uh
everything goes in a particular flow or
um you can say in stepwise. So the first
step it will create an item and it
provide it to the next step. The next
step will take that item and it will do
some updation. So which we'll see.
Okay. But first uh let's create this. So
now that I have this um I can go ahead
and run it in
scratchbook and hopefully u the item
will be added to our type.
Okay. So this the test execution field
and I did this on purpose so that uh we
can have a look at this mandatory
information or you can call it a
prerequisite step before you can run any
TDS modules. Okay. So we need to um have
two uh configuration parameters added
before we can run any uh test data
services u test cases. Okay. So uh we
can either create it uh under
configuration here. Okay. Or uh we can
create it also in our test configuration
parameter where we are creating the test
cases. Okay. So here u like we create
any other test configuration parameter.
We have to add a test configuration
parameter here and we have to name it
test
data
endpoint. Okay. And uh we need to give
it a value. You can see the value is
already populated but it will be your
server address and slash test data
service. For me it is localhost. So I
will give this okay value and then um I
may need to change it uh because my port
is little bit different right it's not
the default port. So let me give it the
port as well otherwise it may uh lead to
some error. So this will be the complete
value and then uh we need to add another
test configuration parameter and that is
the test data repository. So these two
configuration parameters are very
important. Okay, without this uh it
won't work. So test data repository here
we can mention what is our test data
repository name? It was sample
app. Okay. So these are the two test
configuration parameters which you need
to add. And after this you can again try
and execute and this time hopefully it
should be executed and the test data
should be created uh in that particular
type. Okay. So you will not see anything
uh in the logs specifically because it
is creating the test data. But the best
way to verify is to go back to your
server page and just do a refresh here.
Okay. Um, but we did a mistake. I
mentioned a vehicle as uh the type. So,
it created a new type called vehicle and
it inserted the data inside this. So,
you can see a single row right now. And
uh we had another type which we added
right here automo. But that's fine,
right? So, this test case can do both.
it can create a type a new type or it
can write uh create this items into an
existing type as well. Okay. So if I go
ahead right and uh I come here and then
um I change this type okay uh I can
change it to automo you can see it will
be appearing in the drop-down as well.
Now uh now that we have run this once uh
it is able to grab those types. Okay. So
you can easily change this type. Um and
you can again run this. Okay. So I
can this time I can call it Audi. And
then if I run this again, you will see
it will be now creating it uh inside the
automo type.
Okay. So if I go ahead and refresh
this you will see that uh it has now
created another record. Uh the make is
different but all the remaining details
are same. So it is creating a record
inside automo and we have also a vehicle
u type which has got this particular
information. Right. So uh this is how
you can uh use this particular module
create and provide new item to basically
uh create a new type or uh create items
into an existing type. Okay, we'll see
later um how you can randomize this data
and also how you can run this in loop so
that uh it can generate any number of
data for you.
Okay. So uh after this let's go into our
next module okay and uh that is let's go
to add test step and here let's type
test
data and let me expand this so that we
can see this
um and the next step basically is in the
flow is to find and provide item right
so once you create uh and provide the
new item you we need to find it right so
that it can be tracked right and then we
can either do an update or we can insert
something so that uh once we use this
test data it can be uh I mean it is a
used test data right so we need to
update that okay this particular test
data has already been used right so uh
for this uh we need to again put a TDS
type here Okay. So let me call this uh
this time
maybe
vehicle. Okay. So this is our TDS type.
Uh alias name is not mandatory. Uh
position uh we can give a first position
or random position. It will pick up
based on that. Okay. And then u we can
also look at uh a TDQL query. Okay. uh
it is a query which can be easily done
but let's stick to the data search
filter okay and you can also sort your
data based on some values okay so these
are the different uh properties for this
particular module
uh here again uh we are trying to search
a particular data or filter basically
our data based on some particular value
right so what could we could have done
also on this particular data or on this
data structure uh apart from what we
added from the application we should
also add a custom uh item here. Okay. So
um let me add another item here and I'm
going to call this
status. Now the reason for using this
status okay
is we are trying to uh verify what is
the status of the test data because uh
in test data management when the test
data is flowing from one application or
one process to another process we need
to identify what is the state of the
test data. If it is already a used test
data then uh you need to use a different
test data right. So this is a way of
tracking and updating your test data. So
you should always have this field called
status so that you can track uh your
test data uh the status of your test
data whether it has been already used or
not used by the application.
Okay. So now um what I can do here is I
can search based on this particular
custom field. Okay. So I can say here
status and uh once you give this a value
right the status field the action mode
will automatically change to constraint
because we are trying to uh filter out
values based on some uh particular um
some particular data right so it is a
constraint type it is easier to filter
out using the constraint action mode and
that is why by default it will change to
constraint
And here um I'm going to call it status
is new.
Okay. So whatever uh data I have in this
particular table if that particular
status is new then only it will be
filtered and then uh it will be provided
to the next uh process in this complete
flow. Okay.
Um now um it won't be doing much here
right because uh what we are doing is we
are just filtering out the data. So we
would not be able to uh visualize uh
what is happening here. But what we can
do is uh we can basically use something
called uh toka buffer.
Okay. So uh I'll be using set uh
buffer. Okay. Okay. So this is the TBOX
set buffer. I'll give it a name here
called uh
status. Okay. And u then I'm going to
pick up the value uh which has been uh
searched here and it will be providing
us that item right. So what we can do uh
we can grab that item from a TDS
variable. Okay. So here we have to use
this curly brace and then we have to
type TDS. So that will basically grab
the value which has been stored uh in
the memory after it has uh executed this
particular step. Okay. So we are going
to call this
um
vehicle
okay dot
status. So uh you will see if you have
written the syntax correctly it will
show it like this. If not then there is
some problem with the syntax. Okay. So
it is not doing much. uh it is just
setting the buffer so that we can see
the value what uh is the output of this
particular step which is find and
provide item. Okay. So let's go ahead
and run this once again. Uh maybe we
don't want to run the create and provide
new item because uh it is going to again
create a new item. Right? So let's run
these two steps for now.
Okay. Um, this test failed but I know
the reason. Uh, you can see in the log
info that no available test data was
found and that is because I forgot that
we had added a status um recently. So
this data was not created right. So if I
go into uh my test data management under
vehicle, if I refresh, there is no item
called status. Okay. So that status uh
column has not yet been created in our
test data and that is why it is not able
to filter. Okay. So let's do one thing.
Let's go ahead and uh create this
particular
row here or this particular item in this
particular type.
Okay. So what I'm going to do is I am
going to change this to
vehicle.
Okay. And I'm going to now run all the
three steps together and let's see what
happens. Okay.
Okay. So all that steps passed and now
you can see in my set buffer step I can
see the buffer value. Okay. And you can
see that uh it has been set to value
new. So it was successfully able to
create the item. It was successfully
able to find the item and then it was
able to also provide that item into the
next step. where I am trying to grab
that value so that I can see that value.
In a realtime application, what you will
do? You will use the same method but you
will not use maybe the set buffer. Uh
what uh you will do um when you are
taking the application or starting the
application in all these fields you can
grab that value and you can enter in
these particular fields. Okay. uh in the
similar way like I have shown you um you
can use the TDS and then u the
expression where the type dot whatever
item you are trying to access.
Okay. So it's it's just like grabbing
some uh value based on your database
table, right? So based on your records,
you take that particular item and uh the
table name. So table name dot engine
right vehicle.g engine will give this
value. Vehicle doom will give this value
right. So I can grab all these values
and I can then use it in my test cases.
So that's what uh it is doing. Okay. So
that's our uh two modules. Now let's
look at our third module. Okay. And uh
let's search for test data again.
And uh this time I am going to use the
update item.
Okay. So in this update item we have to
give a alias name. Um and this alias
name is like the type. So you can
provide uh here
vehicle. Okay. And then uh in the data
structure uh we have or we can provide
um a item which we want to update.
Right. So what is happening here is I am
now trying to update the status of meta
data that it has already been used.
Okay. So this will basically change uh
the record.
Okay. So this will basically change the
status of this particular record from
new to used. Okay. Because I have
already used this in this particular
step. So um while flowing this data
through the process I'm going to change
the status. Okay. So here I was able to
track the status and here I am able to
update the status of that particular
item. Okay. So this will be now status
used. Um and what we can do is this time
around uh we are going to just uh run
these three
steps and let's see if it uh executes.
Okay. Right. So it
executed and uh now if we can see
whether the item was updated or not.
Again refresh this and come here and you
will see now the status has changed to
used. Okay. So uh this is how you can
track and update the status of your test
data. So individual items you can also
do and update for all these items. Okay.
If you want to uh inside your test cases
using this module test data uh update
item.
Okay. And now um let's go ahead and look
at some more modules. But these are the
important ones.
Okay. But let's have a look what other
modules are present here. So we can
update a type. Okay. Uh we can import
and export items as I said. Um and we
can also move item to a different type.
Okay. So let's let's look at this
particular thing. Okay. So when you have
multiple processes or multiple
applications uh through which your test
case is uh executing right. So if you
want to move a particular item once it's
processed to another uh application or
another process right so for example um
if we have uh filled all the test uh or
all the vehicle data here and then
um while selecting the price option uh
which may be happening at the back end
right it will require all this
information which has been processed or
the test data right and you want to send
this this data to your next process
which is a backend process. So in this
case you need to have different types
right so you'll have a different type
for your backend process and different
type for your front-end process and then
you can basically shift or you can move
your item from your front-end process to
your backend process. Okay. So that way
you can move your test data from one
process to another using this particular
module. Okay. So we have to provide a
existing or new TDS type. Okay. And I'm
going to call it
vehicle actually. um we should have
basically used the vehicle here because
we are trying to move the item from
vehicle into a new TDS type or maybe an
existing TDS type which you have already
created but let's say we have not
created and I want to create it so I'm
going to call it price option uh because
that's where the calculation happens
right so I want to u move this item into
this particular
uh TDS type right so you need to provide
two TDS types. Basically, both could be
existing or one could be new and one
could be existing. Okay. And uh what we
need to do here is uh we need to use the
find and provide item and move item
because until you don't provide the
item, this step cannot execute. If you
try to execute this uh step isolated
right it will fail because it doesn't
have any item um in the memory. Okay. So
you need to run this find and provide
item and then you can move this item to
here. So let's go ahead and run
this. Okay. So this time also it failed.
Now the reason I'm taking you through
all these failures is because you're
going to face this issues if you're not
careful um about how you use these
different modules because each uh module
is basically passing data from one step
to another right so it's basically a
continuous flow if you don't maintain
that flow then you're going to face uh
errors and that's what I'm basically
showing you again you can see here it is
saying no available tested data was
found. Now if you can guess the reason I
have used find and provide item right
and in this I'm trying to search for a
status new. Okay but if you remember in
the previous step we already updated
this item to used. So basically if I go
back to my item there is no such status
new for any particular record or item
right? So that's uh very logical that
the test has failed. Okay. Um now if I
want to use this particular uh move item
to type either I should change this new
to used right or I can run all the steps
uh all together. Okay. So let's go ahead
and run this all together and let's see
if uh it passes this time or not.
Right. So this time it passed and uh now
if you look at this
particular type uh or for our repository
you will see an additional type has been
created which is the price option and
that item has now been moved to this
particular type. Okay. So this is the
Audi and uh it has got the status which
is used which is fine and uh here we
already have these different types or
items
right so uh this is how you can use the
move item to
type and let's look at a final test step
okay and that is to how you can delete a
particular item okay so test data
Okay. And um here is the delete
item. So uh we can delete any particular
item. Um and it could be a existing
alias name which is your type. Right? So
here um it will be the current item not
all the items. So don't worry you will
not be deleting uh all the items. Okay?
But uh if I give a vehicle
right. So what we can do is we can
change the find and provide item from
new to uh used so that I can find a
particular item which is already used.
Okay. And then I can use these two test
steps in conjunction so that I find that
item and I delete it. Okay. So let's do
this.
And let's go ahead and check this
now. Okay. Now you see that uh one item
has been removed which was the used
item. Okay. So this is a way of cleaning
up your data if you don't want to use
the test data which has already been
used by some uh process. So going
forward you can just remove it from your
items so that um you can again go
through the whole process of creating
new test data for your new test
execution.
Right. So uh this is basically the
complete flow. There are some other uh
modules called uh import items and
export items. They are uh pretty much
similar to what we have seen. But there
is one other uh module which could be
useful is uh the expert module. Okay. So
this has got basically a combination of
all your other modules. Okay. So if I
look for the expert
module. Okay. So this expert module has
got a test test data task. And in this
test data task, we have got all the
different uh types or all the different
uh modules which we have used earlier.
Like we can start with create, right? We
can then do a find, we can do a update,
we can delete the item uh uh we can also
do some additional things like we can do
or we can assign that item as read only.
Okay. And uh we can delete type, we can
delete all uh which I would not
recommend you to use. It will delete
everything. And uh we can lock the item,
unlock the item. Uh we can lock the type
and unlock the type. Okay. So these uh
few things or tasks are only available
with expert module. Okay. So you uh you
can either use these individual modules
in your test cases or you can just use
the expert module every time if you want
to perform all these tasks using this
particular module. Okay. Um it's again
the same thing. You need to provide a
TDS type. Uh position is by default one.
You can you can also provide a different
position.
You can provide a a data structure to
filter your particular item and you can
also sort the particular value.
Right? But let's look at an example for
an expert module. Okay. So what I'm
going to do is I'm going to use the find
item here. Okay. Or find task basically.
And then um I'm going to use the vehicle
again here. Okay. uh this time around
I'm going to use the query. So let me
show you the query
expression. So this query expression is
very simple. Okay. Uh it's like uh any
language or English language, right? Or
even if you are familiar with SQL uh it
you can relate to your SQL expressions.
Okay. So if you look at this particular
type, right? We need to first provide a
type and then we need to basically um
give this item name and then the value
dot value right so using this it can uh
find this particular item okay so it's
like a filtering uh the values uh using
a data structure instead of that we can
use a query okay so for this uh we have
to start with vehicle and then square
bracket okay and then I want to use this
make equals equals and
BMW. Okay, so this is a simple
expression. You can see vehicle and make
is BMW. So using this it can filter out
this particular item. Okay. And let's go
ahead and run this. Although we'll not
get any output but the test case will
pass. Okay. Which means it was able to
find this particular item.
So this is how uh you can use all the
different modules to prepare your uh or
manage your test data inside your test
case. Okay. Um as I said you can either
use all the individual modules or you
can use just the expert module to
perform all the different steps and also
you can perform some additional steps uh
in the expert module.
Right now that we are familiar with uh
all the TDS modules, now let's see how
we can apply it back to our test cases.
Right. So if you remember uh we have our
project where we have used the test
design sheet. We have used a template to
uh basically prepare different template
instances based on the test design
sheet. Right? So that's the way of
designing your test cases. And then the
uh test cases were basically uh
referring to the uh Excel sheet which we
had or the design sheet. From there it
was uh getting all the values based on
different conditions and uh different
test cases. Right? So that works pretty
well, right? We have seen that already.
Now if uh you want to use this test data
in your test cases, right? uh and you
can easily integrate this into your
project. All right, but what I'm going
to do, I'm not going to uh disturb this
project because this is already
developed, right? But what I will do is
I'm going to show you how you can
basically create um or use this test
data inside your test case.
Okay. So, um let's go ahead and uh copy
and paste our template. Okay. And this
will create another template. But what I
want to do is I'm going to convert it
into a test case. Okay. So, uh this is
uh basically a simple test case. Now,
it's nowhere uh linked to any test data
sheet. Okay. And uh what I'm going to uh
tell here is
um verify mobile automation insurance.
uh and then I'm going to uh append this
with TDS. Okay. So this implies that
this is using TDS. Okay. And uh in real
time how it will look is you have
everything inside your process your uh
test case whatever it is doing right but
uh inside pre-processing what you can do
is before even opening the application
you can prepare your test data or even
after opening the application uh before
you go uh into the respective fields
where you want that test data you can
basically prepare uh your test data.
Okay. So here um inside pre-processing
let's create another folder and let's
call it prepare test data.
Okay. And now uh inside this prepare
test data I am going to use some of
these things which or these modules
which we have already developed. Okay.
So let's come here and here.
And the first one I'm going to copy and
paste is the test data create and
provide new item. Okay. And then I'm
going to do a find and provide
item. So let's go here and let's paste
it here. Okay. So this will uh create
and provide new item and this will find
and provide the item. Actually we uh
right now we only require these two.
Okay. Because after this uh we are going
to use the values. Whatever uh this item
finds out we are going to use those
values. Okay. Now um inside this right
uh okay so we have got this
and so we have got vehicle. I'm just
checking if everything is still the
same. Okay. uh we are going to use the
status new right now because we have
that
here. So this two uh will work
fine. Now we need to replace the test
data which we have been using from the
Excel sheet and we have to replace it
with the TDS values. Okay. And let me
show you how you can do this. Okay. So
if you want to enter the vehicle data,
this is the data which we'll be creating
in the TDS and uh that's what we want to
use right now instead of this Excel
value. Okay. So again start with TDS and
then uh
vehicle.
Okay. And here uh we are going to use
make. Similarly here DDS okay and
vehicle dot
engine and here so we are going to let's
disable this step or escape the
value okay and here again
TDS vehicle
do. So, let me fill out all these values
quickly. Okay. TDS and vehicle
dot fill.
And this is the last one which is
TDS
vehicle dot
mileage.
Okay, so these are all the values. Um
and let me just cross
check. So we have got the list price.
Okay, all looks
good. So as you can see now we are using
all the TDS values which has been
provided to us from the previous step.
Right? So um now let's go ahead and
execute this and we'll see whether this
works or not. uh we are not going to
execute the whole uh test case because
we haven't replaced everything right now
right so you can do that easily you have
to just follow the same process okay so
um let me run the
pre-processing and uh these three steps
okay but before running this if you
remember we need to set the
configuration parameter and it is always
better you do it at a root level or at a
component level. Okay. So, uh let's look
here where we had this test
configuration parameter and let's see if
I can copy this two parameters or not
maybe
um and here I am going to paste
it. Okay. So, the test data point is
here and the test
repository. Let's come here and paste it
here. Okay. So I have the configuration
parameters. Now let's go back to our
test case and let's try to run this
again. Okay. So we want to run
pre-processing click mobile automo and
uh enter vehicle
data. Okay. So our test passed and you
can see now it has entered values from
the TDS not from the data sheet which we
had prepared or any static values. Right
now where this data comes from is
completely dependent on your
application. Right? It may be coming
from a database. It may be prepared by
the business analyst or it may be
prepared by the manual testing team.
Right? So there are different sources
from where you can generate test data
but uh you can do the test data
management in TDS uh using TUSCa.
Okay. Now as a final step let me show
you how you can generate a bulk test
data with this particular modules. Okay.
Now until now we we have been generating
just one single test data item right uh
whatever values we are providing here
but as I had mentioned earlier we can
randomize all these values okay until
and unless it is not coming uh from a
drop-down like this make uh we cannot
randomize this because it has to match
that particular value from the drop-down
but uh things like this engine right um
or the seeds or uh the test price uh the
mileage these things can be randomized
okay and the way to do is very simple so
use the random uh method okay which we
has used earlier as well so I'm going to
give it a random of three so it always
generates a three-digit number here
similarly for uh this uh seats right
okay uh so I can again randomize this uh
as well I can put a range but for now
it's fine. Okay, I can put a random of
one. This list price um I can put um R&D
of maybe four.
Okay. And uh mileage um I can again put
uh R&D of maybe
three. Okay. So you can see that um I
have put some random values here um and
this will generate some random data
right but uh not only this what I can do
I can also prepare bulk data out of this
right not only single data but bulk data
and how I can do this so let's go ahead
and disable this step for now okay and
this is a folder prepare test data and
go to the properties for this particular
folder. Okay. And if you remember, we
have got this repetition feature. Okay.
So if I give a repetition of
10. Okay. So this is going to generate
uh 10 items with different data because
I have some random values. Obviously
some values will be fixed but all the
other values can be randomized. Okay.
And I can prepare 10 items right with
this particular module by putting this
under a folder and putting repetition.
Okay. So let's go ahead and run
this. Okay. So this is done and you can
see the 10 repetitions. Okay. And if I
go back now to my
TDS. Okay. Now you can see uh there are
10 different values, right? Or 10
different items in my data type vehicle.
So this is one way of uh creating bulk
data from the TDS modules. um you can
put some random value generators and you
can generate uh different test data for
your data type right and then you can
use it inside your test cases okay so
it's a very uh useful uh way of doing it
but as I said the uh data generation can
uh vary and it depends completely on you
how you want to generate your test data
okay but this was all about test data
services. Uh it's a very uh important
feature of Tuska because test data
management is an important part of any
test automation tool or framework.